Guide to the Roslyn Payne Collection of Black Panther Party FBI Files TAM.612
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Roslyn Payne Collection of Black Panther Party FBI Files
1968-2010
1968-1971
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Payne, Roz B. (Roz Berkman), 1940-
United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation
TAM.612
21.5 Linear Feet in 21 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 1 oversize folder
The Roslyn Payne Collection of Black Panther Party FBI Files (1968-2010, bulk 1968-1971) contains files on the Black Panther Party (BPP) created by the FBI's Nixon-era counterintelligence program COINTELPRO. These files consist of FBI reports and memoranda documenting the bureau's use of surveillance, wiretaps, and falsified information in its campaign against BPP. They contain documents collected by the FBI to track the activities of the Black Panthers, which include transcripts of speeches and phone conversations, surveillance reports, interviews, articles, drawings, and related ephemera. These documents were originally released to New York Black Panther Party leader Dhoruba Bin Wahad (formerly Richard Moore) and his attorneys Liz Fink and Bob Boyle following a civil suit they filed against the FBI for withholding evidence in a criminal trial. They were coded an indexed by filmmaker Roslyn (Roz) Payne, who produced a documentary on the Black Panthers and collected a large archive of material related to the history of the BPP. Payne's detailed index is included in the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Roslyn Payne in 2012. The accession number associated with this gift is 2012.021.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series: Series I: FBI Documents; Series II: FBI Documents, Selected by Payne; Series III: Coding Sheets, Series IV: Roslyn Payne Personal Materials. Series I: FBI Documents has been further divided into two subseries, Subseries IA: Index, and Subseries IB: FBI Documents by Section and Serial Number. Subseries IA is arranged by index number and page number. Documents in subseries IB are arranged as they were received from the FBI, and are grouped by section and serial number. Documents in Series II: FBI Documents, Selected are arranged alphabetically by topic. New York COINTELPRO documents in this series were loose in a box and were not grouped topically by Payne. These items have been described as a single unit and maintained in their original order. Documents in Series III: Coding Sheets have not been arranged.
Historical Note
The documents in the Roslyn Payne Collection of Black Panther Party FBI Files (dated 1968-2010, bulk dates 1968-1971) were produced by the FBI's counterintelligence program COINTELPRO. The FBI officially implemented COINTELPRO in 1956 as a consolidated effort to disrupt subversive activities in the United States, focusing originally on the Communist Party of the United States. FBI director J. Edgar Hoover turned the program's attention to black nationalist and civil rights organizations in the summer of 1967, in what he described as an attempt to "expose, disrupt, misdirect, discredit, or otherwise neutralize the activities of black nationalist hate-type organizations." At that time, the Black Panthers had not gained national prominence, and the FBI instead directed its counterintelligence activities toward groups like the Southern Christian Leadership Congress (SCLC), the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), the Revolutionary Action Movement (RAM), and the Nation of Islam (NOI).
The Black Panther Party (BPP) was formed in Oakland, CA in 1966 by Bobby Seale and Huey P. Newton. The Black Panthers grew out of the emerging Black Power movement of the mid-1960s, which contrasted the non-violent civil disobedience of earlier civil rights groups with a more confrontational approach to black activism. Following an ideology of militant self-defense, the BPP sought to promote revolutionary socialism through community-based initiatives. The Black Panthers gained attention for conducting patrols of Oakland neighborhoods, in which party members monitored police activity while openly carrying firearms. They also provided other community services like their Free Breakfast for School Children, which garnered support for the Panthers within urban black communities. The BPP remained a locally-based organization between 1966 and 1968, but began to expand nationally after a series of incidents, including the assassination of Martin Luther King Jr. on April 4, 1968 and the shooting of BPP member Bobby Hutton on April 6, heightened racial tensions in the United States and attracted more black youth to revolutionary politics. By the fall of 1968 the BPP had grown nationally, with offices in twenty cities from New York to Los Angeles. By 1970 the Black Panthers had offices in sixty-eight cities. By the spring of 1969, the BPP had become the primary concern of the FBI and the target of COINTELPRO activities. In an attempt to foster divisions within the party, the FBI sent forged letters, created incendiary propaganda, impersonated and surveilled party members, and wire tapped phones. These efforts resulted in numerous arrests and criminal cases against members of the BPP, some of which were based on dubious evidence. The FBI ceased COINTELPRO activities in 1971, and many of the tactics it employed were later declared unconstitutional.
The COINTELPRO files on the BPP were released to New York Black Panther Party leader Dhoruba Bin Wahad (formerly Richard Moore) and his attorneys Liz Fink and Bob Boyle over the course of several years between the late 1970s and the 1980s. Bin Wahad and his attorneys won the release of these documents following a civil suit they filed against the FBI in the US District Court Southern District of New York for withholding evidence in a criminal trial. Bin Wahad spent 19 years in prison for attempted murder of two New York City police officers, but was exonerated after evidence showed that the FBI withheld crucial information for his defense. Bin Wahad and his attorneys fought for many years to win the release of these documents and eventually used them as evidence to overturn his conviction.
The COINTELPRO files were later indexed by Roslyn Payne, who created a documentary film on the Black Panthers and included a set of these documents in her personal collection on the BPP.
Custodial History
FBI files in this collection were obtained by Dhoruba Bin Wahad and his attorneys Liz Fink and Bob Boyle following a civil suit they filed against the FBI in 1975. The FBI released the documents in stages over the course of several years between the 1970s and 1980s. Roslyn Payne, who worked breifly in the offices of Bin Wahad's lawyers, later indexed these files and included them in her personal archive on the Black Panthers.
Scope and Content Note
The Roslyn Payne Collection of Black Panther Party FBI Files (dated 1968-2010, bulk dates 1968-1971) contains FBI files on the Black Panther Party (BPP) created by the bureau's Nixon-era counterintelligence program COINTELPRO. The files were released to New York Black Panther Party leader Dhoruba Bin Wahad and his attorneys Liz Fink and Bob Boyle, and consist of over 300,000 documents detailing COINTELPRO's attempts to undermine the reputation, unity, and alliances within the BPP. These files are comprised of FBI reports and memoranda detailing the bureau's use of surveillance, wiretaps, and dissemination of falsified correspondence and information. They also contain documents collected by the FBI, which were used to track the activities of BPP members and include transcripts of speeches and phone conversations, surveillance reports, interviews, articles, drawings, and related ephemera.
Because these files contain copies derived from original FBI documents, pages may be redacted and/or illegible. Notwithstanding these redactions and omissions, the documents provide an extensive record of the FBI's campaign against the Black Panthers. These files represent only one copy of the COINTELPRO files released by the FBI. In the mid-1980s, additional set of files were released to Bin Wahad's attorneys that did not contain redactions, but those files are not included in this collection.
The majority of the documents in these files have been coded and indexed by documentary filmmaker Roslyn (Roz) Payne. They come from FBI file number 100-161993, and are grouped by section and serial numbers. Payne's index and coding sheets are also included in the collection and indicate information about topics, groups, or individuals featured in the files, as well as information about regional offices where the documents were sent and received. The collection also includes a set of selected documents, which Payne photocopied from the original set of files received by Bin Wahad's attorneys and grouped by topic. These materials primarily consist of forged letters and propaganda created by the FBI and COINTELPRO documents from New York. A small amount of materials also relate to Payne's work to document the history of the Black Panther Party, and consist of event flyers and community newspaper articles.
African Americans |x History |y 20th century.; Black power.; Racism |z United States |x History |y 20th century.; Federal government records.; Black nationalism.; Bin Wahad, Dhoruba; Black Panther Party; Payne, Roz B. (Roz Berkman), 1940-
- Series I: FBI Documents, 1968-1986; 17.5 Linear Feet in 17 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: FBI Documents makes up the bulk of the collection and consists of 300,000 documents on the Black Panther Party (BPP) released by the FBI, and an index of their contents created by Roslyn Payne in 1986. The files predominantly consist of reports and correspondence between bureau offices that outline FBI counterintelligence strategies and document Black Panther Party activities. Some of these documents include fake letters, flyers, cartoons designed to spread distrust of the BPP, and correspondence detailing intimidation practices used by the FBI against party members. Other documents detail the history and actions of the BPP, and include transcripts of speeches and phone conversations, surveillance reports, interviews, articles, and BPP related ephemera.
  Payne spent many years coding these files to identify topics of inquiry, featured individuals, and FBI offices of origin. Using computer programs from the late 1980s, Payne analyzed the results of her coding efforts and printed data reports based on the categories she selected. These reports allow researchers to search the files by section number, year, recipient, creator, location, featured individual, initials of agent, and various other topics. Two copies of Payne's index are included in this series. Several pages are torn, damaged, or missing from each. Two copies were retained so data missing from one index can be found in the other.
  - Subseries IA: Index, 1986, undated; 0.5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
    Subseries IA: Index contains two copies of Roslyn Payne's index to the Black Panther Party FBI files. Index I appears to be the most up-to-date version of Payne's index, but is missing pages in several sections. Index II is the most complete copy, but appears to be an older version and contains several pages that are bent or ripped. Used together, both copies provide a complete index to the FBI files in Series I.
    Also included in this subseries are several drafts of introductions to the index, prefaces, explanations of variables, and assorted segments. These sections include Payne's annotations and may be useful in providing additional context about the indexing process and documents contained in Subseries IB: FBI Documents by Section and Serial Number. Select portions of the index contained in the assorted segments include the headings: Interesting, People, From, Media2, Faction, and Support.
    - Index I, pages i-xi, 1-452, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
    - Index II, pages i-xix, 1-452, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    - Assorted Segments, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
    - Introductions, Acknowledgements, and Explanation of Variables (various drafts), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Preface, Explanation of Variables, pages 1-14, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subseries IB: FBI Documents by Section and Serial Number, 1968-1977; 17 Linear Feet in 17 record cartons
    Documents in Subseries IB: FBI Documents by Section and Serial Number all come from FBI file number 100-161993, and are comprised of section numbers 2-231. These files are in the original groupings as they were received from the FBI. They contain a variety of documents including FBI memoranda regarding counterintelligence strategies, surveillance reports on members of the Black Panther Party (BPP), fake letters produced by the FBI, and other reports on BPP activities. These files consist of photocopies derived from original FBI documents, and as a result several pages may be illegible, difficult to read, or partially redacted.
    - Section 2, Serial 56-Section 13, Serial 1,050, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Section 14, Serial 1,051-Section 28, Serial 2,090, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    - Section 29, Serial 2,091-Section 40, Serial 3,249, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Section 41, Serial 3,250-Section 54, Serial 4,450, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Section 55, Serial 4,451-Section 71, Serial 5,575, 1969-1977 (Box 6)
    - Section 72, Serial 5,576-Section 85, Serial 6,410, 1969 (Box 7)
    - Section 86, Serial 6,411-Section 98, Serial 7,345, 1969-1970 (Box 8)
    - Section 99, Serial 7,346-Section 111, Serial 8,225, 1970 (Box 9)
    - Section 112, Serial 8,826-Section 122, Serial 9,199, 1970 (Box 10)
    - Section 124, Serial 9,296-Section 135, Serial 10,130, 1970 (Box 11)
    - Section 136, Serial 10,131-Section 147, Serial 10,900, 1970 (Box 12)
    - Section 148, Serial 10,901-Section 158, Serial 11,550, 1970 (Box 13)
    - Section 159, Serial 11,551-Section 167, Serial 12,300, 1970 (Box 14)
    - Section 168, Serial 12,301-Section 179, Serial 13,410, 1970-1971 (Box 15)
    - Section 181, Serial 13,480-Section 191, Serial 14,396, 1970-1971 (Box 16)
    - Section 192, Serial 14,397-Section 200, Serial 15,005, 1970-1971 (Box 17)
    - Section 201, Serial 15,006-Section 226, Serial 16,575, 1971-1973 (Box 18)
    - Section 227, Serial 16,576-Section 231, Serial 16,844A, 1973-1975 (Box 19, Folder 1-6)
- Series II: FBI Documents, Selected by Payne, 1957-1983; 3 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons
  Series II: FBI Documents, Selected by Payne contains three boxes of documents that were photocopied by Payne from the set of bound FBI files and grouped topically. Many of these files relate to fake letters produced by various regional FBI offices in an attempt to spread rumors and misinformation throughout the party. There are also several documents from the New York COINTELPRO file number 100-161140, which relate to BPP activities in New York State and include documents about Dhoruba Bin Wahad. A small selection of these documents contains copies from the FBI Director's office, file number 100-448006. These items were originally loose in a box and were not grouped topically. They are in their original order and described as a single unit.
  - Black, White SDS, More or Peace, 1968-1969 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Detroit, 1968-1970 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Jamal (Eddie) Joseph, 1970-1971 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - FACT, 1968-1970 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - FACT, Huey (by date), 1969-1971 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - FACT, Nation of Islam, 1957-1971 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - FACTionalism, 1968-1971 (Box 19, Folder 13-14)
  - Foreign (by country and city), 1968-1971 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Instructions, 1967-1971 (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
  - Harassment, 1968-1971 (Box 19, Folder 16-17)
  - Information, 1968-1971 (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Notification Program--Copy of File Number 100-161140, Section 5, Serials 511-538, 1976-1979 (Box 20, Folder 3-4)
  - NY COINTELPRO--File Number 100-161140, 1967-1971 (Box 20, Folder 5-15)
  - Packet of Material, 1970 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Phony Leaflet, 1968-1970 (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - Phony Letters--Albany-Chicago, 1969-1971 (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Phony Letters--Cincinnati-Detroit, 1971 (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Phony Letters--Houston-Minneapolis, 1968-1971 (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Phony Letters--Los Angeles, 1968-1969 (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Phony Letters--Newark-N.Y., 1969-1971 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
  - Phony Letters--Norfolk-San Diego, 1968-1971 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Phony Letters--San Francisco, 1969-1971 (Box 21, Folder 4-5)
  - Phony Letters--Savannah-Washington, 1969-1971 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Bert Schneider, 1971-1972 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Jean Seberg, 1970 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Sexual (by city and date), 1968-1970 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Steubenville, 1969 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Supporters, Work--Connections within the BPP, 1970, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Supporters, Work--Outside BPP, 1969-1970 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Women's Movement (by date), 1968-1970 (Box 21, Folder 13)
- Series III: Coding Sheets, 1984-1985, undated; 1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 3 folders
  Series III: Coding Forms consists of one box of coding sheets used by Payne and her assistants to gather data from the FBI documents. Data on these forms was later entered into Payne's data analysis program and printed in the index. Two folders of notes related to the coding process are also included in this series.
  - Coding and Indexing Notes, 1984-1985, undated (Box 21, Folder 14-15, Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Coding Sheets, undated (Box 22)
- Series IV: Roslyn Payne Personal Materials, 1971-2010; 3 folders
  Series IV: Roslyn Payne Personal Materials contains a small assortment of documents related to Payne's work to document the history of the Black Panthers. These items include some newspaper articles and clippings, flyers, and posters related to Payne's documentaries on the Black Panther Party.
  - Articles about Roz Payne's Work on the Black Panthers, 1983, 2001, 2007 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Free Vermont Newspaper Clipping, circa 1971 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - Poster--Black History: Then and Now, 2010 February 10 (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS007, Folder 1)